# Santiago Salas

# Systems Engineer

Pasto, Colombia (GPT-5) (+57) 3113582648 <u>a.santiago.salas.b@gmail.com</u> <u>LinkedIn</u> <u>Portfolio</u> GitHub

**Bilingual Frontend Developer** with more than 4 years of experience, specialized in creating high performance and quality web applications using React. I have collaborated with multidisciplinary teams adopting various development methodologies ensuring an optimized workflow and the delivery of clean and tested code, following principles, patterns and good programming practices. Among my accomplishments is the development of an award-winning virtual and augmented reality application, the best earthquake and volcano viewer in Latin America, and the fastest data training platform for computer vision.

Currently, I am looking for remote work opportunities, where I can apply my technical skills to high-value products and contribute my soft skills to a high-performing work team.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# LinkedAl — November, 2022 - February, 2024

- I significantly improved the usability of the platform, achieving an effective, efficient and satisfactory user experience, with accessibility and customization, which achieved greater user retention and a notable reduction in support and training costs.
- I performed a substantial optimization of the source code, focusing on ensuring scalability and maintenance by
  implementing development principles and best practices which resulted in a clean, standardized and easily
  understandable code for the development team.
- Successfully implemented AI tools for automated image tagging and review, drastically reducing the time needed for this
  process allowing our customers to get faster and more accurate results.
- I developed a high-performance interactive viewer and reviewer for massive image datasets and their segmentation
  masks, this tool allowed users to ensure data quality and streamline the review process, as a result, we increased the
  reliability and accuracy of the data handled.
- Performed a significant reduction in the cyclomatic complexity of components and functions, accompanied by a focus on proper unit test coverage, significantly reducing the possibility of errors and improving the overall user experience.

Tech stack: React, JavaScript, MUI, API Rest, GraphQL, Redux, Jest, Testing Library, Prettier, ESLint, Bitbucket, Jira

#### J&A Real Estate — February, 2022 - September, 2022

I designed and developed the property cataloguing system from scratch, which offers an intuitive visualization, search and
efficient filtering of properties. This system has allowed the company's employees to optimize the organization, increase
productivity, and significantly reduce the time needed to complete various internal tasks, thus improving operational
efficiency in the company.

Tech stack: React, JavaScript, MUI, REST API, Redux, XD, GitLab

# Colombian Geological Service (SGC) — March, 2020 - November, 2021

- I developed from scratch the SGC's earthquake and volcano viewer, which successfully replaced the previous one and is now the best in Latin America, helping millions of Colombians and the Latin American region by providing accurate, interactive and real-time seismological and volcanic information throughout the region.
- I led the optimization of the design of the earthquake viewer at the visual and code level by implementing CSS/Sass methodologies and usability, accessibility and responsive design practices, which achieved a significant improvement in the user experience and also provided the development team with a consistent, readable and easy to maintain style code, optimizing the development process and ensuring scalability in the project.
- I optimized the performance of the earthquake and volcano viewers, improving speed and concurrency, despite managing
  millions of data points and thousands of users in real time. This resulted in a more robust and reliable platform, improving
  the user experience and strengthening our response to geological emergencies.
- I participated in the development of the seismic activity cataloger, allowing the visualization, search and filtering of
  historical seismic data and information in Colombia. Contributing substantially to the analysis, research and prevention of
  seismic events in Colombia.

Tech stack: React, JavaScript, MUI, Sass/CSS, Rest API, Redux, GitLab

# Lobocueros S.A.S — September, 2019 - February, 2020

• I led the design and development of the e-commerce from scratch. The application presents company information, a product catalog with navigation and filtering options, product details, a payment gateway with PayU, forms and a responsive design, this project has allowed online sales to be made with an optimal user experience on any device.

Tech stack: React, JavaScript, MUI, Sass/CSS, REST API, Redux, XD, GitHub

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

<u>Frontend Libraries & Frameworks:</u> Advanced: React, Redux, Astro <u>Programming Languages:</u> Advanced: JavaScript | Basic: TypeScript

Layout Languages and Styles: Advanced: HTML, CSS, Sass

Layout Frameworks & Styles: Advanced: MUI, Intermediate: Tailwind CSS, Basic: Bootstrap

Server Communication: Advanced: Rest API, Axios | Intermediate: GraphQL

<u>Testing:</u> Intermediate: <u>Jest, Testing-Library, Vitest</u> <u>Format & Code Quality:</u> Intermediate: <u>Prettier, ESLint</u> <u>Dependency & Package Management:</u> Advanced: <u>NPM</u>

<u>Development Environments:</u> Advanced: VSCode | Basic: Unity, Android Studio

Development Methodologies and Practices: Scrum, Kanban, Waterfall, BDD, TDD, CI/CD

Development Techniques: OOP, Functional Programming, SOLID, DRY, YAGNI, KISS, Design Patterns

Version control: GitHub, GitLab, BitBucket

Collaborative work: Jira, Slack, Notion, Discord, Trello

### **SOFT SKILLS**

Effective Communication | Teamwork | Problem Solving | Leadership | Continuous learning

#### **LANGUAGES**

Spanish – Native English – B2

#### **EDUCATION**

Universidad Mariana – Pasto, Colombia. Systems Engineer, 2019. (Honorable Mention)

Cambridge Academy – Pasto, Colombia. Level of English B2 (APTIS). 2023. (Meritorious Degree)

#### **AWARDS**

Universidad Mariana - Best Score, Colombian State Tests, Saber Pro – 2019.

CACIED - 3rd Place, Software Engineering (Andean Congress of Computing, Informatics and Education) – 2020

Universidad Mariana - Outstanding Graduate 2021 "Production, Research, Technology and Innovation" – 2021

#### **COURSES**

React, JavaScript, HTML & CSS, Sass, Redux, React Hooks, Unit Testing with JS, Jest, React Hooks, State Handling, Rendering Patterns, Component Compositing, DOM Manipulation, JS Frameworks and Libraries, Asynchronism with JS, Closures and Scope in JS, Load Optimization, TypeScript, Webpack, NPM, ECMAScript 6+, Frontend Development, Git and GitHub, Logical Thinking, Notion, Adobe (XD, Photoshop, Illustrator).